[Music]
[Musique]
I think
i think
American policies are usually dictated
American policies are usually dictated
by amazing ignorance. In the case of
by amazing ignorance in the case of
Libya, for example, I think that the
Libya for example I think that the
Americans who got involved and the
Americans who got involved and the
French
French
[Music]
[Musique]
Hello
bonjour
Thinkerview. Greetings from Berkeley in
thinkerview Je vous salue de Berkley en
[Music]
[Musique]
California. I see that in principle, in
Californie je vois que en principe en
theory, America thinks it has a
théorie l'Amérique pense qu'elle a une
free economy regulated by the
économie libre et qui est réglé par le
open market, but in reality, like everyone else, it's...
marché ouvert mais en vérité comme tout
the dollar is
le monde c'est euh des le dollar est
very weak because America imports
très faible parce que l'Amérique fait
much more than it
beaucoup plus
exports,
d'impimportation que de l'exportation
and this system, which... isn't very, very
et ce système qui euh qui n'est pas
solid. We've seen this in
très très solide euh ce que on a vu des
recent crises, especially in 2007 and 2008.
crises récemment surtout en 2007 2008 et
In that crisis, not
dans cette crise là les banques non non
only US banks, but
seulement des États-Unis mais les
global banks had a crisis due to a lack
banques mondiaux ont eu une crise manque
of capital, which was fueled by
de capitaux qui a été soulevé par la les
illegal funds and black money, as
fonds illégaux et les fonds noirs comme
we say in English, from drug trafficking. We don't
on dit en anglais de du trafic de drogue
know the extent of
et on ne sait pas le grandeur de le
drug trafficking, but we've
trafic de de drogue mais on a fait une
estimated that
estimation que
perhaps
peut-être il y a
a billion dollars a year are
une milliards de dollars par an qui sont
laundered through banks.  And there was
euh blanchi dans les banques et il y a
a United Nations officer who
une un officier de des Nations Unies qui
said that there were banks that
a dit il y avait des banques qui
would have failed during this crisis
auraient échoué pendant cette crise là
if it hadn't been for this
s'il n'y avait pas eu euh cette
remedy for illegal funds
euh remémédiie des des fonds illégaux
in
dans le trafic de
drug trafficking. There are two ways to look at the
drogue il y a deux façons de voir le
role of the war on drugs. For
rôle de la guerre contre la drogue pour
me, the main, most important fact
moi le fait principal le plus important
is that the price of drugs is
c'est que euh le prix des drogues est
much higher than it would be
beaucoup plus élevé que qu'il y aurait
if there weren't this war on drugs.
euh s'il n'y avait pas cette guerre
This means that the
contre le drog ça veut dire que les
big drug kingpins
grands euh rois de la drogue euh il il
approve of this war on
ils approuvent cette guerre contre la
drugs because it's the source of their
drogue parce c'est la source de leur
profit, and drugs become like
profit et c'est la drogue devient comme
a tax on ordinary people
une une taxe euh sur les gens ordinaires
that enriches the rich. And these funds end up
qui enrichi les les riches et ces fonds
in
enfin ils arrivent dans les banques
American banks. The banks make
américaines euh les banques font des
specific arrangements to receive
arrangement spécifiques pour recevoir
these private funds. There's the
ces fonds pr privés il y a la banque
ordinary bank, and then alongside it, the
ordinaire et puis à côté la banque
private bank that receives illegal fortunes,
privée qui reçoit des fortunes illégales
like that of, for example, the brother of the
comme celle par exemple de du frère du
late president of Mexico. And so, the
feu président de du Mexique et comme ça
result is that...
euh le résultat c'est que
Drugs are even more
la drogue est même plus
important to the economy
important dans l'économie
than they would be if we didn't have
qu' ne serait si nous nousavions pas pas
this war on drugs.
cette guerre contre la drogue
Yes, it's true that
oui c'est vrai que pour
for states, when I talk about
les pour les états quand je parle par
California for example,
exemple de la Californie
our number one
là notre premier
agricultural product is
produit agronome c'est le
marijuana, but it's true that there isn't
marijuana mais c'est vrai que il n'y a
a tax on marijuana because it's
pas une taxe sur le marijuana par ce
not legal. It's starting to change a little,
n'est pas légal ça commence à changer un
but in principle it's illegal, it's
petit peu mais en principe c'est illégal
not taxed,
ce n'est pas taxé
and the government suffers.
et le gouvernement souffre euh
The economy is different because
l'économie c'est différent parce que
even if we're now talking about
même si nous parlons maintenant de
heroin coming from
l'héroï qui proviennent de
Afghanistan, the big profits aren't
l'Afghanistan les grands profits non ne
made in
sont pas fait en
Afghanistan, the country of production; they're
Afghanistan le pays de production il ils
in the country of consumption.
sont dans le pays de consommation
Because it's
parce
estimated that maybe 80% or more
que on estime que peut-être 80 ou plus
of the profit is made in those countries,
80 % du profit est fait dans ces pays-là
and even the other profits are
et même les autres euh profits sont
also banked in a country where the
aussi banqués dans un pays où les
banks are stable and guaranteed,
banques sont fermes et garanties
that is to say, the
c'est-à-dire les
United States. There have been two times when the
États-Unis il y a eu deux moments où les
United States intervened in
États-Unis se sont intervenus en
Afghanistan. The first was against
Afghanistan le premierre était contre
the Russians and Soviets.
les les les russes et soviétiques en 19
1979 and the second, obviously after September 11,
79 et le deuxe évidemment après le le 11
2001. The result of these two
2001 le résultat de ces deux
interventions is that
interventions c'est que
Afghanistan, which has always had
l'Afghanistan qui a toujours eu euh
opium, hashish, and marijuana,
de de lopium et de hashich de marijuana
but before the first
mais avant la première
American intervention, was
américaine intervention américaine
n't a power in the
n'était pas une puissance dans le marché
international market. Consumption was
international la consommation était
local, and even the Americans went there to have a
locale et même les américains ils sont
safe drug experience in the 70s. It was what was
sans sans danger dans les années 70
called the
c'était le ce qu'on appelit le la piste
Hippie Trail,
des des hippies le hippy trail
but from almost nothing in 1979
mais de presque rien en 1979
until now,
jusqu'à maintenant maintenant c'est
almost 90% of the international heroin
presque 90 % de l'héroï internationale
comes from Afghanistan, and even in the
provient de de l'Afghanistan et même aux
United States, if I can add another
États-Unis si je peux ajouter un autre
figure, the percentage of
chiffre il y avait euh le percentage de
heroin in the United States that came from
l'héroï aux États-Unis qui provenait de
what is called the "crescent" outside
ce qu'on appelle le croissant dehor
was zero in
c'était zéro en
1979, and according to the government, in
1979 et selon le gouvernement en
1980 it jumped to 60%.
1980 ça a sauté jusqu'à 60
[Music]
[Musique]
We see in Washington, there is this
personnes on voit à Washington il y a ce
big drug problem.  And there are
grand problème de la drogue et il y a
sociologists, doctors, all
des des sociologues des médecins toutes
sorts of experts who say that
sortes d'experts qui disent que
the law really needs to be changed, and
il il faut vraiment changer la loi et
especially, to begin with, that
surtout pour commencer légaliser le
marijuana should be legalized. But it's a taboo subject in
marinoana mais c'est un sujet interdit à
Washington. No one wants to discuss it if they want to
Washington personne c'est si on veut si
pursue a
on veut poursuivre une carrière
political career; they shouldn't get involved in this
politique il faut pas se mêler de ce
issue. And I think the reason is
problème et la raison je pense c'est
because there's too much money and too much
parce que il y a trop trop d'argent et
profit coming from the
trop de profit à qui provient de la
current situation. That's why it's
situation actuelle
an example—not the
et c'est pour ça c'est un exemple pas le
only one—where our democracy isn't working
seul où notre démocratie ne fonctionne
because money prevents
pas parce que les l'argent interdit la
discussion of real problems.
discussion des vrais problèmes dont la
Drugs are truly one of the major
drogue est vraiment une des grands
problems that are ruining
problèmes qui rouinent
life in big
euh les les la vie dans dans les grandes
cities, the inner city as we
villes euh le inner city comme nous
say in English.
disons en anglais
And for 50 years we've waited for a
et pendant 50 ans on a attendu une
change in the laws, but it's a
changement de des lois mais c'est
taboo subject. Is it
interdit comme sujet c'est est-ce que
because politicians
c'est parce que les les les politiciens
aren't free? Yes, they're free
ne sont pas libres oui ils sont libres
to discuss it if they want, but they
de le discuter s'ils veulent mais ils
know very well that it will be the end of
savent très bien que ce sera la fin de
their careers, so that's why they
leur leur carrière alors pour ça il le
discuss it.
discut
In my life, I've only spent six
euh j'ai dans ma vie je n'ai passé que 6
months in Washington. I don't know
mois à Washington je je connais
Washington very well, but I saw an
Washington très mal mais j'ai vu une une
example in Congress of the
une exemple au congrès de la de
way in which you're not
de la façon dans laquelle on n'est pas
allowed to talk about
permis de parler de la
drugs. I was part of a
drogue je faisais partie d'une
secret committee. We received
commission secrète CD on on recevait des
speeches in a private room for
discours dans une chambre privée pour
one of the House committees,
une des commissions de la
and the
et
chairman of that committee
le le président de cette commission a
told the committee that there was a word he
dit au comm ement que il y a un mot
absolutely didn't want to
qu'il voulait pas absolument voulait pas
hear in the discussion, and that word
entendre dans la discussion et cette mot
was legalization.
était legalization
I wondered why, but
et je me suis demandé pourquoi mais plus
later I did some research. I found
tard j'ai fait de recherches j'ai trouvé
that this representative in the House
que c ce représentant dans la chambre
had a brother. What do we
avait un frère avec une
say is,
qu'est-ce qu'on dit est
he was a lawyer, and in his
euh il était avocat et dans son bureau
law firm, he had a very important
des avocats il avait un très grand
client. He was one of the biggest
client c'était un des plus grands rois
drug kingpins in New York City.
de la drogue dans la ville de New York
So, he was a source of information about
alors c'était une source de profil euh
someone who had been damaged, and drugs
qui qui aurait été abîmé et la drogue
had been legalized. And that's why,
avait été légalisé et c'est c'est c'est
I believe, this individual,
pour ça je crois pour cet individu mais
who was a...  A rather important individual, by
qui était un individu assez important
the way, who didn't want to hear
d'ailleurs euh qui voulait pas entendre
the word "
le mot
legalization," it's true. There are also
legalisation c'est vrai aussi il y a des
large bureaucracies, like the DI, which
grandes bureaucraties comme le di le qui
is in charge of preventing drug trafficking, and
est chargé de d'empêcher la la drogue et
like all the prisons, and all these
comme tes les prisons et toutes ces
bureaucracies become part of the
bureaucratie deviennent une partie du
system that governs the country. They don't want
système qui gouverne le pays ils veulent
change. It was like in
pas avir un changement c'était comme
the 1920s in the United States
dans les années 20 au aux États-Unis
with Prohibition. It was becoming increasingly
avec la prohibition euh que de plus en
obvious that
plus c'était évident qu'il fallait
change was necessary, but at that time there was
changer mais il y avait à cette époque
also great resistance
aussi une grande résistance qui
coming from the bureaucracy. And elsewhere,
provenait de la bureaucratie et ailleurs
when alcohol was finally legalized, that's when
quand enfin on a légalis l'alcool c'est
drug prosecutions intensified, and
haussé la la poursuite des drogues et
people who previously looked for
les gens qui anciennement cherchai de
alcohol were now
les boîtes de de l'alcool maintenant il
looking for marijuana for the
cherchaient le marijuana pour la
first time. It was right
première fois c'était tout de suite
after the end of
après le le la fin de la prohibition de
alcohol prohibition. I have a weakness:
l'alcool j'ai une faiblesse c'est que
I invent words from time to time,
j'invente des mots de temps en temps
like "deep politics," and
comme la politique profonde et aussi
I also invented this phrase, "
j'ai inventé cette phrase
superworld." There's an "underworld" in English.
supramonde il y a en anglais un underwor
and which exerts power over
sousmonde et qui fait une puissance sur
the government below, but it's
le gouvernement d'en bas mais c'est
much weaker than the power
beaucoup plus faible que les puissances
over the government above. And
sur le gouvernement d'en haut et
I call all this private force—
j'appelle tout cette force privée les
corporations, but also individuals,
corporations mais aussi des individus
the very rich—
des Très Riches
uh, the very rich who are involved in
euh les très riches qui s'occupent de la
politics, I call them the
politique je je les je les appelle le
superworld. And in my
soupremonde et dans mon
book, "The Road to World Disorder,"
bouquin ici la route vers le désordre
I even gave a definition, which I
j'ai même donné une définition que je
'll read now, and for that I'll need my
vais lire et pour ça il me faudra mes
glasses for a moment: the
lunettes une instant
superworld, uh, the
supramonde
realm of the rich and
euh la le royaume de la société riche et
privileged society, which is the scene of
privilégié qui est le théâtre d'une
effective influence exerted on the
influence efficace exercée sur le
government by private power. Although the
gouvernement par le pouvoir privé bien
superworld is not
que le supremonde ne soit pas
institutionalized or
institutionnalisé ni autorisé
formally authorized to exert such influence,
formellement exercer une telle influence
it includes, firstly, those whose influence is
il inclut d'abord ceux dont l'influence
exerted through their wealth, whether
s'exerce à travers leur richesse qu'elle
administered personally or more
soit administré personnellement ou plus
traditionally through
traditionnellement par le billet des
tax-exempt foundations and the
fondations exonorées d'impôts et les
projects they support. And
projets qu'ell soutiennent et
secondly, the representatives of the first—
deuxièmement les représentants des prem
this term must be distinguished from
ce terme doit être distingué de celui de
Friedrich Lundberg's—the super-rich,
frériich Lundberg les super riches
that is to say, the 60  The
c'est-à-dire les 60 familles les plus
wealthiest families in the United States, which he erroneously predicted
riches des États-Unis dont il a prédit
in
d'une manière éronée en
1967 in his book *The 1967 Family* would
1967 dans son ouvrage 6ty families
continue to dominate the
qu'elle continuerait à dominer les
United States as much as the class and
États-Unis autant que classe et
government of
gouvernement de
money, are shown in recent rankings
l'argent les récents classements u
by Forbes magazine of the 400
établi par la revue Forbes dans des 400
richest Americans. This demonstrates
états-uniens les plus riches démontre
that Lunberg was wrong
que lunberg s'est
on two counts: the wealthiest
trompé sur deux plans les plus riches
heirs of the 1967 generation are
héritiers du M 67 ne sont
not, by any means, the richest people
magitoritairement pas les plus riches
today, and the richest people
d'aujourd'hui et les plus riches
today are not necessarily
d'aujourd'hui ne sont pas nécessairement
those who
ceux qui
project their wealth onto
projetteent leur richesse dans le
political power. Furthermore, the
pouvoir politique par ailleurs le
upper class is not a class but
soupremonde n'est pas une classe mais
a category—this is very important. One
une catégorie ça c'est très important il
must not think that this class is
faut pas penser que cette classe est
unified. The rich
unifié les riches les riches se
know each other, but they do not act in a
connaissent euh mais il n'ag ils
unified way.
n'agissent pas d'une façon un solidaire
It is wrong to conceive of
il est éronné de concevoir comme une
the influence of the
règle institutionnelle l'influence du
upper class, as exercised through
suamonde telle qu'était exercé à travers
the
la société
Bilderberg Group, the Trilateral Commission, or
Bilderberg la commission trilatéral ou
the Council on
le conseil de relations
Foreign Relations, as an institutional rule. However, there are
étrangères cependant il existe des
Lesser-known and usually
cabales moins connu et habituellement
secretive cabals thrive within these
sérète qui prospère au sein de ces
high-society circles. For example, in France, the
supramonde par exemple en France la
Piné Circle or the Safari Club—that's my
cercle piné ou le safari club c'est ma
definition. It's true they are
définition c'est vrai qu'ils sont
organized. It's true that there are,
organis organisés c'est vrai qu'il
for example, Davos every year,
existe par exemple Davos chaque année il
the Bilderberg Group, the
existe la société Bilderberg il existe
Trilateral Commission, and the very existence
Commission Trilatérale et le fait même
of all these different organizations
de toutes ces organisations différentes
indicates a rather
indique que c'est une situation plutôt
pluralistic than unified situation. But in the
pluraliste que unifiée mais dans au
middle of it all, you really have to realize
milieu il faut vraiment se rendre compte
that, for
que par
example, not everyone knows this, but
exemple pas tout le monde le sait mais
it's true that in
c'est vrai que en
1974, I believe, the Wilson government in
19 74 je crois le gouvernement Wilson en
England was overthrown, ousted, and also
Angleterre a été bouleversé a mis à la
de Gaulle, at the end of his term,
et aussi de Gaul à la fin de son pouvoir
had problems with his intelligence service.
avait des problèmes avec son service
And we later learned that there was
et nous avons appris plus tard qu'il
a Piné Circle that
existait une cercle piné qui prenait euh
was proud of the party that had been able to
euh qui était fier de la fête qui elle
elect Mrs. Thatcher in England.
élire Madame Thatcher en Angleterre et
And so, there are not
et alors il y a pas
just organizations, but even
même organisation mais même des des
deep powers in the middle of this high-society
puissances profondes au milieu de ce
world because the power of money
suprmonde parce que la force de l'argent
is very, very strong. For example,  We
c'est très très for par exemple euh nous
know very well that there were two
savons très bien que il y a eu deux
oil price hikes, the
haussements de tarif pour la pétrole la
first in
première en
'72, I'd say '19-72-13, and the second in
72 je dirais 19 72 13 et le 2è
'79-'80. We know that Nixon was
1979 80 euh nous savons que Nixon était
responsible for the first one because it
responsable pour le premier parce que ça
helped his projects to
a aidé ces projets
settle the
régler la région du
Iranian Gulf region—do we say the Gulf?—because
golf iranien est-ce qu'on dit la Golf en
the programs for Iran and
tout parce que les prof fit pour l'Iran
Saudi Arabia, which came from the
l'Arabie Saoudite qui provenait du
oil price hikes, paid for their
haussement de pétrole payé pour leur
import of American weapons, with
importation des armes américaines avec
teams
des des équipes
to teach the use of these
pour pour enseigner l'emploi de ses
weapons and all that. The second one, obviously
armes et tout ça le deuxème évidemment
under President Carter, didn't help
sous le présidence du président Carter
his
ce n'était pas ça n'aidit pas de tout sa
policy at all; on the contrary, it was
politique au contraire c'était
responsible for his downfall. But I believe
responsable pour sa chute mais je crois
that the Republicans had
que les républicains avaient des
contacts in the oil-producing countries, and
contacts dans les pays pétrolières et
perhaps Bippi in particular,
peut-être bipi en particulier euh ont
encouraged OPEC to raise the price
encourager OPEC de hausser euh le prix
of oil. And in this way, we saw
de pétrole et par cette façon on a vu
the almost simultaneous election of Sergey in
l'élection presque simultanée de s en
England and then also Rean in the
Angleterre et puis aussi euh reen aux
United States. And really, the election of
États-Unis et vraiment l'élection du
President
président
Rean was the  The beginning of a new
Rean était le début d'une nouvelle
era in the United States, marked by a
époque aux États-Unis où il y a eu une
significant increase in subsidies for
grande haussement de subventions pour
military budgets and the
les des budgets militaires et pour les
CIA's operating budget. The CIA even started
budgets sucret de CIA le CIA commencé
a war in Afghanistan, and
une guerre en Afghanistan
we're seeing a result
et tout ça et on voit un résultat
in civil society. Before
dans la société civil que avant
1980, the rich and poor classes
1980 les classes riches et pauvres
were approaching each other in terms of income; there was
s'approchait dans le revenu il y avait
a decrease in the disparity between
une diminution de la disparité entre les
rich and poor. But since that
riches et les pauvres mais depuis ce
year, since 1980,
cette année-là depuis 1980
it's the opposite: now the
c'est le contraire que maintenant les
rich are getting much richer
riches deviennent beaucoup plus riches
and the poor much poorer.
et les pauvres beaucoup plus pauvres et
We are now in a more precarious position than Europe,
nous sommes PIR maintenant que l'Europe
statistically
cette dans dans dans ce ce statistique
speaking. Before 1940,
c'est-à-dire avant avant 1940 80 euh
England was a
l'Angleterre était euh une pays de
class-based country with rich and poor, and
classe avec des riches et des pauvres et
the United States less so. Now it's the
les États-Unis moins maintenant c'est le
opposite: America is more divided
contraire l'Amérique est plus divisée
between rich and poor than
entre les riches et les pauvres que
England, or almost any
l'Angleterre ou presque n'importe quel
other country in Europe, except Russia.
autre pays euh en Europe sauf la Russie
When I talk about the superpower, you should
quand je parle de la supramande il faut
n't think that the superpower is
pas penser que le la supramande est
divided by a
divisée par une
huge gap.  Well, not from the government, it's
grande grand fossé euh du gouvernement
the source of people, especially in
non c'est la source des gens surtout
the past. People entered from the upper echelons,
dans le passé les gens entrraaient de du
they entered the
supronde ils sont entrés dans le
government, and especially the position of, uh,
gouvernement et surtout au poste euh le
Secretary of the Treasury, Secretary of the
secrétaire de finances secrétaire du du
Treasury, as we say,
trésorerie est-ce qu'on dit
uh, but there was also an institution in the
euh mais aussi il y a une institution au
middle of the government that
milieu du gouvernement qui était qui
received much more of the thinking, the
recevait beaucoup plus les la pensée les
direction from Wall Street than the rest of the
direction de Wall Street que le reste du
government, and that was the CIA. The
gouvernement et c'était le CIA le CIA
CIA, uh, when it was created, it was
euh le CIA quand a été créé c'était
really a Wall Street creation.
vraiment une création de Wall Street
Truman was the president; he wasn't very comfortable
Truman était le président il n'était pas
with this idea of ​​having
très à l'aise avec cette idée d'avoir
an intelligence service in
une service d'intelligence dans de
peacetime conditions, but it was Wall
conditions de paix mais c'était Wall
Street that insisted. CIA, Wall Street, that
Street qui a insisté CIT Wall Street qui
won. And it's very interesting to
a gagné et c'est très intéressant de
see that Truman insisted that the chief
voir que Truman insistait que le chef
in his time, the chief, was
dans son son époque le chef n'était
never from Wall Street, always from
jamais de Wall Street toujours de
Central America,
l'Amérique centrale
especially from the
surtout de de
military, before Allan Dallas, who was
l'armée avant Allan Dallas qui était
obviously pure Wall Street,
évidemment Wall Street purure
uh, there was never a chief who
euh n'y avait jamais un un chef qui
came from Wall Street, but the
provenait de Wall Street mais les
deputy chiefs, all the deputy chiefs that we
sous-chefs t tous les souschef que nous
We know SEP, I know SEP, they
connaissons SEP je connais SEP ils
were all on Wall Street, and in addition there's what's called
étaient tous W Street et en plus il y a
the Society Register, which
ce qu'on appelle le Society register ça
means people of inherited wealth, uh, the
dire des gens de richesse hérité euh la
great society of New York, 6 of this 7, was part
grande société de New York 6 de ce 7
of this society, this Social Register.
étit de cette société ce social register
So from the beginning it was a
alors dès le commencement c'était une
creation of Wall Street, and finally,
création de Wall Street et enfin
for technical reasons that I
pour des raisons techniques dont je
discuss in my
parle dans mon
book, *American War Machine*, it was
book mon bouquin American War Machine
Trump who brought in Allan
c'était trum qui a fait introduire Allan
Dallas as one of his deputy chiefs in the
Dallas comme un de ses souschef dans le
CIA. But the moment the Republicans
CIA mais le moment que les républicains
finally won the presidency in
ont enfin gagné le présidence en
1952, it was the end of the army chiefs,
1952 c'était la fin des chefs de l'armée
George Beatles Smith, and it's the
c'est G Beatles Smith et c'est le
beginning of the Dallus era, a
commencement de l'époque de dallus un
Dallus who was at the CIA, and Are Dallus, his
dallus qui était au CIA et are Dall son
brother, who was the Secretary of State. And it's at
frère qui était le secrétaire d'État et
this time that we saw a
c'est nous avons vu à cette époque une
pure Wall Street policy, beginning
politique pure de Wall Street commençant
with,
avec
uh, assistance in uplifting the
euh l'assistance pour soulever le
president-elect in Iran, Mr. Mossadeq,
président élu en Iran monsieur mosadeek
to ​​save the
pour sauver le
Anglo-Iranian oil company, which is now called
anglo-iranienne qui maintenant s'appelle
BP, and secondly, immediately after
BP et deuxièmement tout de suite après
in Guatemala
en Guatemala
to
pour
save United Fruit
sauver United Fruit
against
contre
another elected president, Arbens,
en contre un autre président élu arbens
elected not in a
élu pas une façon
ticking way. It must be remembered that Truman,
tique il faut se rappeler que Truman
in
en en
creating the CIA, thought it would be
créant cette CIA il pensait que ce
an intelligence service to
serait un service d'intelligence de
find out
renseignement de de trouver des des
information from all countries, but from the very
nouvelle de tous les pays mais euh dès
beginning, under the direction of people
commencement sous la direction des gens
from Wall Street, they got involved in
de Wall Street ils sont entrés dans les
operations—that is to say,
opérations c'est-à-dire des des
criminal operations in general—in the
opérations criminel en général dans le
rest of the world because it was partly due to the
le reste du monde parce que c'était à
Soviet threat
cause en partie de de menace soviétique
at the time. The first Operation C was to
à l'époque la première opération C et de
put money into the Italian election
mettre argent dans l'élection italienne
of 1948,
de 1948
and it was said that the Russians
et on disait que les les Russes
were doing the same thing, so they had to
faisaient la même chose alors il il
do the same thing. But in
fallait faire la même chose mais dans
the 1950s, yes, all the
les années 50 oui toutes les opérations
CIA's major operations
du CIA des grandes opérations ils
were for the good of Wall Street,
étaient euh pour le bien du Wall Street
and we don't know that because
et euh on on ne sait pas ça parce
the CIA also got involved in
que le CIA a aussi s mêlé dans le
Southeast Asia, starting first in
sud-est l'Asie en commençant d'abord en
Thailand, then Burma, then
Thaïlande et puis Birmanie et puis le
Laos, and finally, on a much larger scale,
Laos et enfin d'une façon beaucoup plus
Vietnam. I would say that from the
vietnamment je dire dirait que dès le
From the very
dès le
beginning, the
commencement les
CIA interventions were for the goals
interventions du CIA étai pour les buts
defined by Wall Street. First,
définis par Wall Street d'abord c'est à
we're talking about the
ce moment-ci nous parlons du Conseil des
Council on
relations extérieures de Council of
Foreign Relations, which had a
foreign relations qui avait eu une
discussion about what should be done in
discussion ce qu'on devrait faire en
Guatemala before the CIA got involved. So,
Guatemala avant que le CIA a commencé
first, a
alors premièrement
discussion in New York, a decision, and then a
discussion à New York décision et puis
decision communicated to
décision communiqué à
Washington. This was under
Washington c'était c'était sous
Eisenhauer, who was very willing;
eisenhauer qui était très volontairement
he agreed. But the way to
il était d'accord mais la façon de
influence policy was
d'influencer la politique c'était à
primarily through the CIA, and it was
surtout à travers le CIA et ça a été
executed by the CIA. And I see the same
exécuté par le CIA et je je vois la même
thing later with Vietnam because,
chose plus tard avec Vietnam parce que
for me, Vietnam was the
euh Vietnam euh était un pour moi la la
real reason for intervening in Vietnam in
vraie raison euh pour avoir intervenu
1966. It was because,
euh en VI au Vietnam c'était à cause que
with the technical developments in
avec les développements techniques de
oil exploration, for the
des recherches de pétrole pour la
first time, oil could be found
première fois on pouvait trouver de de
under the sea. And we
pétrole au-dessous de la mer et on
knew from the beginning of the
savait dès dès le commencement des
1950s that there was a lot of oil
années 50 qu'il y avait beaucoup d'huile
in, under, the Chinese sea, the
dans au au sous la mer chinoise le le la
sea between Vietnam and
mer entre le Vietnam et
Indonesia. And we see...  This
l'Indonésie et nous voyons à cette
era of major US interventions
époque des grandes interventions des C
in Vietnam and Indonesia, and after that,
au Vietnam et à l'Indonésie et après ça
the signing of contracts with
les euh la signature des contrats avec
American companies to
les les compagnies américaines pour
develop oil under the sea in
développer le l'huile sous la mer au
Vietnam, Cambodia, Thailand, and
Vietnam au Cambodge au Thaïlande et
especially
surtout à
Indonesia, is when I really began
l'Indonésie j'ai débuté vraiment dans
my research by looking for the reason
mes recherches en cherchant la raison
why the Americans
pour laquelle les Américains se sont
intervened in
intervenus dans la politique
Indonesian politics in
indonésienne en
1965. The result was a massive massacre
1965 avec le résultat un grand mass cre
of perhaps millions of people—
de peut-être millions de personnes
civilians, women, children, entire classes,
personnes civiles femmes
institutions, schools—because they
institutions dans les écoles parce
were part of a communist party,
qu'ils étaient dans un parti communiste
but a fairly peaceful one
mais un parti communiste assez pacifique
that hoped to win an election. This was one of the
qui comptait gagner une élection ça
major
c'était une une des grandes
interventions by the United States, not
interventions euh des États-Unis non
only the CIA but also the
seulement le CIA mais aussi l'armée
American military, with all sorts of
américaine avec le avec toutes sortes de
things involved. But it was for
choses mais c'était pour le
oil, for the
pétrole le réérique à la fois c'était
region's natural resources. We talked about rubber, we
région on a parlé de caoutchou on a
talked about tungsten,
parlé de
all of that wasn't wrong.
étin tout ça ce nétait pas fausse c'est
It was especially important to note that one of the biggest, least
il comptait surtout une des plus grands
discussed, but very important,
moins moins discuté mais très important
resources was tungsten. I don't know
c'était le vfam tungsten je connais pas
the word in French; I hope it's...
le mot en français j'espère que c'est
Tungsten is tungsten in English, and
tungsten c'est tungsten en anglais et
it's absolutely necessary for
c'est absolument nécessaire pour une
strong steel, for components in
acier fort pour les mement dans les
armored vehicles, and so on. It was absolutely
chats blindés et cetera et absolument
essential, and at that time it came
nécessaire et ça provenait dans cette
from China, which is
époque de la Chine qui qui était
now out of the question, and also from
maintenant hors hors de question et
Southeast Asia. That was also true, but
sud-est ça c'était vrai aussi mais le
oil has overtaken the others, I think,
pétrole a dépassé je crois les autres
especially rubber, because now
surtout le caoutchu parce que maintenant
most of our rubber comes from oil. It's
la plupart de notre caoutchu ça provient
artificial,
de la la pétrole euh c'est artificiel
and we'll see in the statistics that
et on on vait voir dans les statistiques
trade between Southeast Asia
euh la commerce entre l'Asie du Sud-Est
and America was based on oil.
et l'Amérique était basé sur le pétrole
The investments we saw in
les investissements qu'on a vu dans
Southeast Asia
l'Asie du Sud-Est une grande partie part
also came largely from Japan, but Japan's
aussi du Japon mais le Japon aussi était
economy after the war was also
son son économie après la guerre était
a creation of the
une cré des des
Americans because we think that at that time
Américains parce qu'on pense à cette
American policy was
époque que la politique américaine était
defined by the Cold War against
définie par la guerre froide contre la
Russia and the Soviet Union. We wonder to what
Russie contre l'Union soviétique on se
extent this
que en quelle partie cette cette guerre
Cold War was real and to what extent it was
froide et était vrai et en quelle partie
a kind of mask for the
c'était une espèce de de masque pour les
more capitalist reasons of Wall
raison plus capitaliste de de Wall
Street. My personal opinion  I've thought about it a
Street mon opinion personnellement j'ai
lot because I was
j'y a réfléchi beaucoup parce que
young at the time, but I
j'étais jeune à C cette époque mais je
remember it well: partly, the
le rappelle bien c'est que en partie la
fear of the Soviet Union was real, and
peur de l'Union soviétique était réel et
true. That is to say,
et et était vrai c'est-à-dire
I don't believe the Soviet Union would ever have
que je crois pas jamais jamais l'Union
invaded Western Europe with its
invadé l'Europe deouest avec ses ses
divisions into Eastern Europe, and that's
division en l'Europe de l'Est et ça
the great myth of NATO. And when
c'est le grand mythe de l'UTAN et quand
I was...  In the government, I
j'étais dans le gouvernement j'ai
started to question this myth. I didn't
commencé à questionner ce mythe je je ne
believe it at the time, and I don't believe it
croyais pas à cette époque je le VO pas
now, but I believe it's very, very
maintenant mais je crois c'est très très
possible that the communist parties
possible que les les partis communistes
in Italy and France would have won
en Italie et en France auraient gagné
their elections. It's because the
leurs élections et c'est parce que le
CIA intervened to prevent this
CIA est intervenu pour empêcher C ce
result that we now see a
résultat que nous voyons maintenant une
non-communist Europe. And from my
Europe non communiste et de mon point de
personal point of view, I don't like the
vue personnel je je n'aime pas les
methods that were used to
moyens euh qui ont été utilisés euh pour
protect Western Europe, but I
protéger l'Europe de l'Ouest mais je
'm very glad that we do
suis très content que nous voyons
n't see a France that suffered the same
pas une France qui a subi la même
post-war policies as, for
politique après les guerre que par
example, Poland, because I lived
exemple la Pologne parce que j'ai vécu
in Poland. It wasn't so bad; I
en Pologne c'était pas si pire j'ai je
knew people in the
connaissais les gens dans le
socialist government, they were my
gouvernement socialiste ils étaient mes
friends, but it was
copains mais
sad for Poland.
euh c'est c'était triste pour la Pologne
And I'm glad that Poland is
et je suis content que la Pologne est
now free from Russian influence.
maintenant libre de l'influence russe
And for me personally, I believe
et pour moi personnellement je crois
that the events in France would have been just as
que les événements en France aent été
sad if the communists had been
aussi triste si les les communistes
put in power. These are
étaient mis au pouvoir ce sont des
subjects that are very difficult to
sujets qui sont très difficile à
discuss,
discuter
but I said all this to admit
mais j'ai dit tout ça pour admettre
that there was a  There was an element of truth at the
qu'il y avait un élément de vérité au
beginning of the Cold War, but
commencement dans la guerre froide mais
it's also important to see that as this
aussi il faut voir que quand cette
war developed, it was increasingly
guerre s'est développée ça a été de plus
influenced by the private interests of the
influencé par euh les intérêts privés du
global elite.
supremonde
I'll
j'ai j'ai j'ai je vais inclure
now include the major
maintenant aussi les grandes
international corporations of the time,
corporations internationales de l'époque
which were primarily
qui étaient surtout les les corporations
oil corporations like Standard Oil, what
de pétrole comme Standard Oil ex ce que
we now call Exodus Mobile, and
nous appelons maintenant exon mobile
Texaco.
Texaco
The Cold War evolved over
euh c'est la guerre froide s'est
the years into
changé pendant des années pour devenir
a way to protect the interests of
une façon pour protéger des intérêts de
these large
ces grandes
corporations, not
corporations non pas
exclusively in Europe, but partly in Europe
ement en Europe mais en parti en Europe
with the Truman Doctrine. To
avec le Truman doctrine euh pour
guarantee a non-communist Greece, it was
garantir une grissce non communiste
accepted at the time that this was to ensure
c'était admis que c'était pour garantir
that Saudi Arabian oil
euh que le pétrole de l'Arabie saoudite
could be sold in Europe
pourrait pourrait être vendu en Europe
because
parce que
the major corporations didn't
les grandes compagnes Corporation ne
want it to come from the
voulaient pas que ça provienne aux
United States, since they still had
États-Unis parce qu'ils avaient encore
domestic production here.
une production domestique ici
This oil had to go to
auanis il fallait que ce pétrole aille à
Europe, and for that, a
l'Europe et pour ça il fallait avoir une
non-communist Greece was necessary. That was the
Grèce non communiste ça c'était un
beginning of a mixing of interests.  Between the
commencement de de mélange entre la
real Cold War and the interests
vraie guerre froide et les intéressants
of the Corporation, but later it was
de le Corporation mais plus tard c'était
almost purely the corporations,
presque purement les corporations
yes, I just wrote a short article
oui je viens d'écrire un petit article
on the current situation in mid-
sur la la situation actuelle au milieu
2013 in Syria because it's a choice
2013 en Syrie parce que c'est un choix
that has been repeated many times in
qui s'est reproduit m fois dans
American history: a choice between a
américaine choix entre une politique
military policy and a diplomatic policy. It was
militaire et une politique diplomatique
at the beginning of
euh c'était au commencement du mois de
May that the United States and Russia agreed
mai que euh les États-Unis et la Russie
that they needed to
se sont accordés qu'il fallait euh
agree on a convention, perhaps in
convenir une convention peut-être à
Geneva, to seek an
Genève pour chercher une solution
international diplomatic solution to the
internationale diplomatique au
Syrian problems, which were becoming increasingly
problèmes syriens qui devenaiit de plus
serious and threatening to escalate beyond
en plus grave et qui menaçait de plus en
Syrian borders and create a
frontières syriennes et de créer une
crisis
crise
in Lebanon, Iraq, and even perhaps
euh au Liban en Irak et même peut-être
Turkey,
en en Turquie
because there are CDES (Councils of Economic and Social Rights) everywhere. And
euh parce qu'il y a des CDES partout
I was very disappointed that Obama,
et euh j'étais très déçu que enfin Obama
who was in a very narrow position, didn't
qui est pris en position très
want to get involved
euh rétréci il ne voulait pas se mêler
in this affair, but under
dans cette effaire mais enfin sous la
pressure from the fascists in Washington,
pression des fauxcans euh à Washington
he
et elle
agreed to send weapons, small
a accordé envoyé des armes des petites
arms.  But weapons, uh, to the fighters,
armes mais des armes euh aux combattant
and that's a joke because
et c'est un c'est une blague parce que
the CIA had already sent not
déjà le CIA il avait envoyé non pas
only weapons but also
seulement des armes mais aussi des euh
specialists to train them. It's
des spécialistes pour enseigner dans les
a bit like Libya; there was
armes c'est un peu comme la Libye il y
a secret policy that was already
avait une politique secret qui déjà
underway. This policy is
commençait cette politique ça ça c'est
very dangerous for an
très dangereux pour une solution euh
international diplomatic solution. Hope isn't completely extinguished,
diplomatique international euh l'espoir
but it's
n'est pas tout à fait éteint mais c'est
much weaker now. The
beaucoup plus faible maintenant le
problem is that in Syria, as
problème c'est que dans la Syrie comme
in the other countries I've mentioned, there's
dans les autres pays dont j'ai parlé il
an oil problem. Now it's
y a un problème de pétrole il maintenant
increasingly gas. Before, it was oil,
c'est de plus en plus le gaz avant
now it's
c'était l'huile le pétrole maintenant
increasingly gas. We've even
c'est de plus en plus le gaz on a
discovered gas in Syria. But what
découvert du gaz même en Syrie mais ce
's much more important
qui est beaucoup plus important
is what we call a gas field, a
c'est comment on dit un gaz field un
gas field, a region of underground gas. It's
gaz une région de gaz sous terre c'est
under the Gulf, which is shared
sous la sous la Golfe qui est partagé à
half by Qatar and half by Iran,
moitié pour le Qatar moitié pour l'Iran
and it's the
et c'est le c'est la région le plus
largest region in the world. The market for
grand dans tout le monde le marché pour
this gas will be Europe, and the
ce gaz ce sera l'Europe et les conduit
gas pipelines won't pass through  Israel will
de gaz ne passeront pas par Israël ils
go through Syria as usual. There was
passeront par la Syrie comme d'habitude
the first
il y avait la première conduit de
oil pipeline from Saudi Arabia that went through
pétrole de l'Arabie Saoudite passé par
Iraq and finally from Syria to the
l'Irak et enfin la Syrie à la
Mediterranean. That was built a
Méditerranée ça a été TER mené il y a
long time ago. There was another pipeline
longtemps il y avait une autre conduit
that was damaged during the Iraq War,
qui était abîmé pendant la guerre d'Irak
but now it's a choice. Qatar
mais maintenant c'est un choix euh Qatar
told Mr. Assad in Syria, "
a dit eu monsieur Assad en Syrie il faut
You must
que vous vous
resign. We want a
démissionner nous voulons un
more Muslim government that would
gouvernement plus musulmane qui
allow our gas pipeline to pass
laisserait notre conduit de gaz de passé
from Iraq to Turkey because there is
de l'Irak à Turquie parce qu'il y a
now a large gas pipeline.
maintenant une grande conduit de gaz
When will the Nabuo Line be built
quand va construire le la ligne nabouo
in Turkey? Qatar wanted to sell its
en Turquie et Qatar voulait vendre son
gas through this pipeline,
gaz à cette ligne
but at the same time, Iran
mais à la fois simultanément l'Iran a
said, "We also want to take gas from
dit nous voulons aussi prendre de gaz de
this same region and send it to
cette même région et de l'envoyer en
Europe through a pipeline that would pass through Iran
Europe par une condu qui passerait Iran
and Iraq because now Iraq is
et Irak parce que maintenant l'Irak est
much closer to Iran than before."
beaucoup plus proche à l'Iran que avant
And
et
finally, Syria
enfin Syrie
and this war
et cette guerre
between the government on one side and the
entre le gouvernement d'un côté et les
different factions,
différentses parties
including the rebels, are for a reason,
de entre les rebelles euh il le raison
and it was subsidized mainly by
et sétait subventionné surtout par le
Qatar, which has already
Qatar qui a qui a déjà
paid.  I believe there's over 3 billion
euh payer je crois plus de 3 milliards
dollars in subsidies for this
de dollars de subvention pour cette
revolt because they want
révolte parce qu'ils veulent
Assad out to secure their
avoir Assad à la porte pour avoir leur
pipeline, but Assad is protected
conduit mais Assad est protégé
now. He's starting to win with
maintenant il il commence à gagner avec
the support of those who are directly
l'appui deb là qui est directement
subsidized and partly directed by Iran.
subventionné et en parti dirigé de
Assad signed an
Terran en en en Iran et Assad a signé un
official contract with Iran for
contrat officiel avec l'Iran pour avoir
a gas pipeline that would run
un conduit de gaz qui passerait
directly from Iran to a port—I think it's called the
directement on appelle ça je crois le le
Islamic Gas Pipeline—which will
islamique qui passera de de de
now connect Iran to a
l'Iran a maintenant un port qui
port that was previously quite small
anciennement était un port assez petit
but will certainly become much
mais qui deviendra assurément beaucoup
larger because of the gas. Even there, even
plus grand à cause de gaz même là-bas
in Syria,
même en Syrie même
and like the Great Britain, most
et comme la la GR la grande partie des
American interventions,
interventions de de l'Amérique et deess
especially in
n'importe où et surtout au
Libya and Iran, were about
liby et en ir
oil and gas.
il s'agissait du pétrole du gaz et la
Syria is no exception; it was more
Syrie n'est pas une exception euh mais
like Afghanistan.
c'est plutôt c'était comme l'Afghanistan
Because when the
même parce que le moment
United States started to
où les États-Unis commençaient à
take an interest in the
s'intéresser à la fin des avec le
Taliban at the end of the
taliban la fin la fin des années
1980s, there was talk of...  of an
1980 il avait on parlait de conduitire
oil pipeline that would pass from
de pétrole qui qui passerait de
Kazakhstan to Pakistan through
Kazakhstan à Pakistan à travers
Afghanistan, that's why Unocal, an
l'Afghanistan c'est pour ça l'unocal une
American company, invited people,
compagnie américaine a invité des gens
representatives of the Taliban, to come to
les représentants de taliban de venir à
Texas to be taught
Texas pour être enseigné dans les
technical matters. It's always about
affaires techniques euh c'est toujours
oil when we talk about
le pétrole quand quand on parle de
America and its Petrodollar, which is
l'Amérique et son Petro dollar qui est
the basis of its international wealth.
les bases de sa sa fortune
America is divided between hawks
l'Amérique euh est divisée entre des
and doves on the issue
faucans et des colombes sur le le théma
of Syria. And in Europe, it's
de du Syrie euh et mais en Europe c'est
the same situation, but there's an
le même situation mais enore il y a une
even more serious division because there are
division encore plus grave parce qu'il y
two kinds of interests in Europe.
a deux sorte de des intérêts en Europe
Small countries like Austria in the East
des petits pays comme Autriche à l'Est
want to have
ils veulent avoir
gas as soon as possible; they don't want to
euh de gaz aussitôt que possible ils
be under
veulent pas être sous
too deep an influence from
euh l'influence trop profonde de de la
Russia, so they invite
Russie alors ils invitent cette la
France, on the contrary, which has
France au contraire euh qui avait des
historical interests in the region.
intérêts historiques dans la région
Austria is perhaps one of the
et euh l'Autriche est peut-être une des
doves of Europe, and France
colombes de l'Europe et la France
is currently one of the hawks of
actuellement est une des faucon de
Europe, as it was also in the
l'Europe tel qu'elle était aussi dans la
case of Libya.  Bernard Levi, who
cas de la Libye c'était Bernard Levi qui
in a sense initiated all the
a dans un sens débutter tous les
problems in Libya in
problèmes au liby en 19 2000
2000-2011, is why these
2011 c'est pour ça que c'est ces
gas and oil problems
problèmes de de gaz et de pétrole ne
are not simple. They create
sont pas simples il créent des des des
regional alliances, and especially
alliances régionales et surtout aussi la
Russia has a rather complicated position regarding
Russie a position assez compliquée à
this oil pipeline because
travers ce conduit de pétrole parce que
I imagine Russia preferred to avoid
je j'imagine que la Russie préférait de
both the Qatari and
voit ni le le conduit de Qatar ni le
Iranian pipelines, as the
conduit de l'Iran parce que le marché de
gas market is not
gaz n'est pas
infinite and is limited. Currently, it's
infini est limité et actuellement c'est
Russian gas. To conclude,
russe pour termin
I would like to say something to the
je voudrais euh dire quelque chose à la
young people attending this interview.
jeunesse qui assiste à cette interview
I would like to talk about why
euh je voudrais parler de la raison pour
I do my research and
laquelle je fais mes recherches et j'ai
investigations. First, I
fait mes enquêtes
come from Canada, which is
d'abord je je je viens du Canada qui est
a fairly small country in terms of
un pays assez petit si on parle de du
population. In Canada, we have
nombre de gens et nous avons au Canada
the impression that if we have an idea
l'impression que si nous avons une idée
to improve the country, we can
pour améliorer le pays nous pouvons le
share it with leaders in Ottawa,
partager avec les dirigeants à ottoa
with members of the Canadian Parliament.
avec les membres du Parlement canadien
And in fact, I did this a little bit
et même en vérité j'ai je l'ai fait un
when I was young.  Even before
petit peu quand j'étais jeune même avant
the age of 20,
l'âge de 20 ans
and when I arrived in the
euh et comme je suis arrivé aux
United States, I had the same illusion, but
États-Unis j'avais la même illusion mais
you know very well that it's not the
vous savez très bien que c'est pas la
same in the United States as, and there are
même chose aux États-Unis que euh et il
more people in California alone, I
y a plus de gens en Californie seul je
think, than in all of Canada. So it's on a completely
crois que dans tout le Canada alors
different scale. And I must say that, if
différente et je dois dire que euh si
I had the idea at the beginning, I was
j'avais l'idée au commencement je
fighting against intervention in the
luttais contre l'intervention dans la
Vietnam War. From my career in
guerre du Vietnam je de ma carrière dans
diplomacy, I knew a little bit about
la diplomatie je connaissais un tout
the Vietnamese situation,
petit peu de la situation vietnamienne
not much, but enough to
pas beaucoup mais assez pour me
convince me that the United States should
convaincre que les États-Unis ne devrai
not enter this war, for
pas entrer dans cette guerre pour pour
American health as much as for
pour la santé américaine aussi autant
Vietnamese health.
que la santé Vietnam vietnamienne
And I learned that a whole
et j'ai bien appris que tout un
movement, thousands,
mouvement des milliers des milliers
almost millions, in the end, they
presque de millions à la fin ils ont
helped a little to end
assisté un tout petit peu à terminé
this war,
cette guerre
but
mais
my
mon ma
personal contribution was very, very
contribution personnelle était très très
small, and I don't feel now
petite et je n'ai pas maintenant
that my ideas are going to change
l'impression que mes idées vont changer
the United States, not at all. But still,
les États-Unis pas du tout mais quand
I'm very happy to be doing what
même je suis très content de faire ce
I'm doing. I meet people who
que je fais je je rencontre des gens que
I love being here with people. I'm in a
j'adore comme des gens je suis dans une
room here with friends I
chambre ici avec avec de copains que
met through a movement, and through
j'ai rencontré dans un mouvement et dans
these
ces
movements I meet people I love. I also always have this
mouvements je rencontre les gens que
idea that even if
aussi j'ai toujours l'idée que même si
I do
je
n't contribute to
cont contribue pas aux politiques de la
current policies, there's always the
du présent que il y a toujours la
politics of the future, and maybe
politique de l'avenir et que peut-être
I can persuade other people to be like
je peux persuader des autres gens d'être
me, interested in international justice,
comme moi euh intéressé dans la justice
personal freedom, and democracy. It's
personnelle et dans la démocratie euh
on the screen at the
c'est sur l'écran de le niveau de
Washington level; it's a very bad
Washington c'est un très mauvais
movement, a very bad time
mouvement mouvement très mauvais moment
now for justice, freedom, and
maintenant pour la justice la liberté à
democracy. But still, I see
la démocratie mais quand même je vois
that
que les
Washington's bad policies are creating opposition, and I
Washington crée une opposition euh et je
absolutely want to be part of
veux absolument je veux être parti de
that opposition because I have faith
cette opposition parce que j'ai la foi
in humanity, that we have a
dans la race humaine que nous avons une
tendency towards
tendance enfin
democracy, towards freedom,
vers la démocratie vers la liberté
and towards the joy of being free in
et euh vers la joie d'être euh libre
a free and open society.
dans une s société libre et ouverte
I'm very disappointed if I didn't think
et je suis très déçu si je ne pensais
I could contribute even a little bit
pas que je pourrais contribuer un tout
to that future, and I
petit peu à cet avenir et je veux
hope that among you, you
j'espère que parmi vous autres vous
young people, I'll be there too.  Well, there will be
autres la jeunesse euh il y aura des
people who will have the same hope of
gens qui vont avoir la même espoir de
participating in the future of our country, of
participer dans l'avenir de notre pays
our globe, and of our
de de notre globe euh euh et notre race
human race. Thank you very much.
humaine merci
And there is currently a
beaucoup et il y a actuellement une
situation that we wouldn't have foreseen
situation qu'on n'aurait pas prévu il y
20 years ago. In fact, there's a comparison between
a 20 ans en fait des comparaison entre
the United States with its
les États-Unis avec leur
universal surveillance
surveillance universelle
and East Germany during the
et l'Allemagne de l'Est à l'époque de
Stasi era, where the same thing existed. And this is
stasie où il y avait la même chose et
one of the major indications that
c'est une des grandes indications que
since 9/11 we have
depuis le 11 septembre nous avons
really seen a big change in the United States.
vraiment vu un grand changement aux
We wouldn't have foreseen this
États-Unis on n'aurait pas prévu cette
universal surveillance, and that was
surveillance universelle et ça c'était
a result of what we
un résultat de ce qu'on
call Continuity of Government
appelle continuity of government
Arrangements (COG),
arrangements le COG continuité de
which had been
gouvernement qui avait été planifié
planned for 20 years by a
planifié pendant 20 ans par un
group of people, partly in the
groupement des gens par en parti dans le
government and partly outside. The most
gouvernement et en parti dehors le plus
interesting thing is that two of these people
intéressant c'est que deux de ces gens
who planned it were Donald Ramsfeld
qui ont planifié était Donald ramsfeld
and Richard Shane, who was in power in
et Richard Shany qui étit au pouvoir à
Washington on 9/11.
Washington le le 11 septembre le
President Bush was in Florida, and
président Bush était en Floride et ces
these two people started
jeux là ces deux gens-là ils ont fait
implementing the
commencer implémenter les prov provision
Continuity of Government Provisions.  They
de continuity of government
can be summarized in three
et on peut les résumés en trois
categories: first,
catégories d'abord surveillance
universal surveillance without a court warrant;
universelle sans mandat de d'une cour et
second, and
deuxièmement qui était beaucoup plus
I believe much worse, indefinite detention without a
pire je crois détention indéfinie sans
warrant; and third,
sans mandat d'un cours et troisièmement
the permanent intervention of
l'intervention euh permanent euh du de
the military in
l'armée de des militaires dans la
domestic security in the
sécurité domestique euh des
United States. Points 2 and 3 were
États-Unis les points 2 et 3 étaient
against existing laws, one
contre les lois existants même on
could even say against the United States Constitution. It
pourrait dire contre la Constitution des
really needs to be explained to a
vraiment il faut expliquer au à une
French audience that the idea of
assistance française que l'idée euh de
indefinite detention without a warrant contravenes one of the
sans mandat indéfini ça contrevient une
deepest and
des libertés les plus profondes et les
most
plus euh
traditional freedoms of the
traditionnelles de la tradition
Anglo-Saxon tradition. This was granted by
anglosaxone ça ça a été donné par le
Magna Carter in
magna Carter dans l'année
1215, and since then we have had what is
1215 et depuis ce tempslà nous avons eu
called habus corpus, which
ce qu'on appelle euh habus corpus qui
states that someone is
qui dit un cours euh c'est quelqu'un est
detained for 24 to 48 hours. But soon,
détenu dans 24 48 he mais mais bientôt
it becomes necessary to produce
il faut euh produire
the person who was detained. And although
ce le type qui a été détenu et bien que
I believe it's horrible that we
je crois que c'est horrible que nous
now have
avons maintenant une surveillance
universal surveillance to find
universelle euh pour trouver des
terrorists, we have found perhaps
terroristes on a trouvé peut-être une
twenty  Around fifty, it depends on
vingtaine une cinquantaine ça dépend de
your definition,
votre définition
but certainly fewer than 500
mais moins de certainement moins de 500
terrorists in the United States.
terroristes aux États-Unis on en
Everyone is monitored,
surveille tout le monde et et
constantly, all the time, and this has
permanemment tout le temps et ça ça
become an excuse to control the
devenu une excuse pour contrôler le
public in
public en
general, to create a situation very, very
général pour créer une situation très
similar to what the
très similaire que ce que le le
novelist George Orwell warned about in
romancier George Orwell a prévenu dans
his novel
son roman
1994. He got the date wrong, but he
1994 il s'est trompé de date mais il a
really did warn about what we have
vraiment prévenu ce que nous avons
now in the United States. And also the
maintenant aux États-Unis et aussi le
third
trisème
point: the permanent intervention of the military in
point l'intervention des militaire dans
domestic security. There are also
sécurité domestique il y a aussi les
specifically American laws, like the ones that
lois spécifiquement
prohibited this, and all of that
interdisait cela et ça tout à tout a
changed, apparently forever, at 10:00
changé apparemment pour toujours à 10h
AM on September 11th when Charles and
le matin du 11 septembre quand ch et
Romsfield implemented the
romsfield ont fait implémenter les
provisions for continued operation.
provisions de continue
The result is that we
le résultat c'est que nous
have the public state
avons l'état public quiue
as before, but we
comme auparavant mais nous avons
now have a second state, a
maintenant un deuxième état un état
secret state, or as we are
sécré ou comme on commence à dire de
increasingly saying, a deep state, which is
plus en plus un état profond qui n'est
not governed by the
pas gouverné par le
Supreme Court, which makes its own laws.
Cour suprême qui fait ses proes loi
There  Now, there are some
euh il y a maintenant des des des
very technical questions, and I won't go into
questions très techniques où je je vais
those issues in this
entrer dans ces problèmes dans ce
speech, but it's not just
discours mais c'est pas seulement
me talking about a deep state in the United States
moi-même qui parle d'un état profond
now. Even
maintenant aux États-Unis et même des
academics are saying there was a coup d'
gens de des des académiciens qui parlent
état on September 11th because it's such a
d'État le 11 septembre parce que c'est
change in the
un tel changement de la condition
country's political situation. It's true that we need to
politique du pays c'est vrai qu'il faut
recognize similarities
des euh des reconnaître des similitudes
with the situation in
avec la situation dans l'Allemagne de
East Germany. And for a country like America, which was
l'Est et pour un pays comme l'Amérique
born in
était qui est né dans des
conditions of revolution against
conditionitions de euh révolution contre
an
un gouvernement
absolutist government in London that didn't listen to
absolutiste à Londes qui n'écoutait pas
local interests, it's
les intérêts locals c'est c'est vrai
truly dramatic to see the
c'est vraiment dramatique de voir le
change we've seen in this
changement qu'on a vu dans ce
country. It's very sad. But we
pays c'est très triste c'est
mustn't think that the
mais il faut pas penser que le
public is dead, that the public has forgotten
public est mort que la public oublié
the idea of
l'idée de la
freedom. It's very difficult to
liberté c'est très difficile de
generalize about the situation in the
généraliser au de la condition des
United States, and the moment we think we
États-Unis et le moment qu'on pense
understand this...  What's happening in the
qu'on a comprend ce qui passe aux
United States is the moment when a
États-Unis c'est le moment que un
new movement appears elsewhere, one that wasn't expected,
nouveau mouvement paraît ailleurs qu'on
and that's why I have no doubt
n'attendait pas et c'est pour ça j'ai je
that the government will
n'ai aucune fois que le gouvernement va
correct the
corriger la condition des conditions
current situation, but I
actuellement actuelles mais j'ai
truly believe that there will finally be
vraiment confiance qu'il y aurait enfin
change
un changement qui
coming from the public, from people like me
proviendra du public des gens comme moi
and my friends in the
et mes copains dans le
anti-war movement. There aren't many guys like Kusac,
antig-uerre des types comme kusac il y
this
en a pas il y en a pas beaucoup cette
incredible Adonis-like figure who, looking everyone
espèce d'aplon incroyable avec lequel
in the eye,
les les yeux dans les yeux de tout le
said, "I'm not lying, you
monde il a dit je ne mens pas vous
can believe me," and so on. There was something about it: how can we
pouvez me croire et cetera il y avait un
imagine that a
truc comment peut-on imaginer que un
politician will be able to say, "
politicien va être en mesure de se dire
No, no, wait, the general interest is
non non attendez l'intérêt général c'est
the defense of fundamental freedoms. A
la défense des libertés fondamentales
fundamental freedom is the defense of
liberté fondamentale c'est la défense de
privacy," and there's a
la vie privée et là il y a un
conflict there. It's impossible to call for
conflit c'est impossible d'appel les
compassion in France. The problem is that
haœurs en France le problème c'est que
the word "compassion" is demonized. We
le mot à cœur est est diabolisé on
simply forget that these are people who
oublie simplement que ce sont des gens
prioritize results over
qui qui privilégie les résultats sur les
methods, and who...  are capable of gaining
méthodes et qui sont capables de gagner
an intimate knowledge of a system
une connaissance intime d'un système